if you have a very specific expectation
about what it's going to do for you like
I'm going to have this libido I'm going
to have you know erection every morning
I'm going to just jump out of bed and
want to go work out and it's just going
to be great you're G to be disappointed
because it's not going to do that for
you you just hopefully feel a little
better but don't forget you can't out
Human Being Human there's no drug that
you will take that will out human you
being a
human so welcome back to the trt and
hormone optim ation YouTube channel with
two guests today we have with us Dr Kei
Nichols and Amir kti welcome back guys
good to see you Steve good to see you
here nice thank you too Dr Keith you're
uh you've been an inspiration since I've
been uh on trt for a very long time so
to be on with both Stephen and you is an
honor so thank you both you guys for
being on here thank you thank you as
well my pleas welcome so Amir today
we're talking about the mindset we need
to start or be on trt and Dr Kei Nichols
is going to help us with those uh things
so maybe start out Amir why did you want
to talk about that so interesting last
podcast we did was on PFS and there the
biggest thing that I got out of that I
got I got a lot of emails a lot of
social media messages that said that was
very powerful that was so impactful
there were so many things that I needed
to hear number one getting off social
media and getting off a lot of those um
like Reddit and things like that and
spending five hours a night in the when
you should be sleeping getting on those
forums and trying to figure out what to
do instead of getting a professional to
fix you things like that so I was
getting like what do you do for for uh
feeling better how do you explain it to
your wife what about when your friends
ask you what should I not tell people
all these questions that started to come
up so I thought it' be valuable not just
for people who have PFS but people in
general men in general I'm going to
speak for men because I'm a man so men
in general that trt is not just sticking
yourself with a needle and
then be an amazing time or putting on
transcrotal cream and things just
magically start to get better there's a
lot of things that we don't take into
account that will exponentially make
this journey much better than not than
just doing what we call testosterone
replacement therapy that's one of the
aspects that I think is extremely
important but if you don't have the
other variables figured out it's not
going to just be uh roses in a beautiful
beautiful time if that makes sense and
you know and I'm we were talking before
the show Keith said you know this is
going to be your your podcast but to be
honest Keith you know like I've already
mentioned he's an incredible wealth of
knowledge and I'd love to have his you
know take on it as we as we progress on
this
call right be glad to enjoy the PFS
podcast I was able to watch it uh twice
at least and uh enjoyed a lot of the the
points and I uh was extremely pleased
with your points on social media and
Forum so be glad to to touch more on
that as you get going here today but uh
that was great inside great advice and
I've tried to give that advice for years
but uh but certainly we'll talk more
about that today
absolutely and um what would you tell uh
men that are experiencing low te
symptoms um before they go to their
provider is there a certain mindset they
need to get in touch with the doctor so
that's a really good question what to do
beforehand so here's something one of my
colleagues I do I do Executive coaching
and I own restaurants I've written books
worked at a Recovery Center all that
aside um why I'm s why I just told you
that is because when I had low te
symptoms I did not want to write a book
I did not want to go to my stores I did
not want to spend I I just wanted to do
nothing and I had PFS which was really
really exhausting so here's a couple
things that I think are incredibly
valuable when I found out that not only
did I have low testosterone I had what's
called postfastr syndrome which messed
up my libido I had suicide liation I had
a host of mental physical and you can
even say spiritual like I was messed up
all over the place and one of the things
my colleague had pointed out a long time
ago and I actually wrote it down I have
a couple notes here he said if you're
doing things in order to be happy you
are doing it in the wrong order okay
this is very important if you're doing
things in order to be happy then you're
doing it in the wrong order what does
that mean so once I found out what was
going on with me a lot of people do this
thing where they say once I get
fixed then I'll have a good life once I
get better then then I'll go back to my
life and live it once I get my hormones
in check then I will X Y and Z which is
extremely
backwards the whole point of why we do
trt or why I wanted to get my hormones
fixed is to live to to live a happy life
and my wife pointed out as well as well
why don't you live a happy life now why
wait right this idea that this magic
thing is going to happen in the future
here's something I tell you as an adult
you might fix your hormones today
someone might have cancer tomorrow you
might fix your hormones today you may
lose day so if you have this idea that
once you get somewhere then you'll live
your life I'm I'm not I don't want to
bust you guys as bubble there such thing
because life is a contact sport and if
you're waiting for all the Ducks to be
in a row you're not gonna it's not going
to work out so rule number one for
people who are going to their doctor
right make a commitment and you'll
notice something Dr Keith Nichols and Dr
DeVos they're they're doctors and look
how fit they are they're fit and I I
assure you that they were this is a
lifestyle that they've had right so rule
number one is when I was on my lowest
part of my life those are the moments I
made the biggest commitments what were
those commitments that I'm going to
spend time with my family that I'm going
to try to work out the best I could it
was very difficult with PFS so my wife
would say get your butt outside and
let's go walk even though I could barely
lift a weight she made me move so couple
things when you're just starting where
you found out that your testosterone's
low start making commitments today at
your lowest points don't wait until you
eight months from now when you think
you're going to be at your Peak and
because sometimes it takes a long time
right so make those commitments now what
does that mean start doing things you
can do right now eat right sleep get off
the
forums go read a good book at night
instead of being on those forums
scrolling learn
something right go buy get a book on on
on educating yourself about hormones
educ educating yourself about how to eat
properly how to work out like spend time
becoming a better man as you go on your
journey to fix your hormones because
what I've noticed with a lot of men do
is they have this waiting game no I'll
do that
afterwards it's a terrible strategy
because afterwards I will assure you you
will find other things that you will
find wrong and if your
mindset continues to be that way then
you're always going to have that carrot
dangling in front front of you waiting
for the perfect time to live your life
and and Keith I don't know if that's
something you you agree with or disagree
with or I agree with thought on that uh
agree with it you you'll hear me hear me
say it all the time you're right you do
have to first and foremost make a
commitment to self-improvement you have
to make that commitment and then once
you do that you you've got to be willing
to sacrifice and what you have that many
men don't have air but they're looking
for and they think that maybe
testosterone will provide it for them
but it will not you know once you've
accomplished your commitment and your
willing to to really truly
sacrifice uh then you really have to
have the determination the strength
the endurance and the discipline to
really see it through and what you had
was extreme discipline you had extreme
determination you had extreme strength
not just physical we're talking about
the mental strength to force yourself to
do something that you didn't feel like
doing I've been there as well you know
we say it all the time motivation comes
from within you're not going to take
testosterone all of a sudden wake up
motivated you're not going to undo do
years of you know bad eating bad
lifestyle bad habits you're still going
to have those habits when you start you
have to be willing to make that
commitment to break those habits but
that takes motivation which comes from
within if you can't find it we can't
provide it for you in the form of a
syringe or a cream or a gel you you've
got to be able to do that yourself and
air many men just aren't ready or maybe
don't know how I find most of my job a
lot of times is about coaching and
hormones will not overcome life they
will not overcome life we're taking men
that have symptoms of a deficieny
and we're improving those symptoms we're
giving them testosterone to overcome the
symptoms but then that makes them a
normal individual subject to all the
problems that we as humans have and that
affects how we feel and function every
day so I couldn't be more on board with
what you're saying love to would love to
hear more absolutely and so I'll give
you an example of uh well said by the
way the one of an example is I had a
gentleman private message me and said
you know I I I think I have PFS
post finasterid syndrome and um My Le my
libido seems to be worse than it was
last year I didn't know what he looked
like didn't know who he was I said let
me ask you something how how old are you
and how much do you weigh and how tall
are you I think he was 34 years old 5
foot6 240 pounds okay yeah now men that
are listening to this
call I have have no idea I'm first of
all I'm not a medical doctor okay so I'm
not speaking from that perspective but I
will tell you when you're 240 pounds and
you're 5 foot6 you have way too many
variables to know what the heck is going
on with your body here's what I did okay
when I went as Stephen going back to
Steph's question what if your
testosterone's low right when I went to
my doctor I try to remove every single
possible variable I could before showed
up to the doctor because he didn't have
to say to me well you have to work on
your weight you're inflamed because
you're eating a bunch of trash you don't
seem to be out in nature so we don't
know if it's a you're you know or you're
you're stressed out all of those those
things can mess and can look very
identical to people that have low
testosterone I have friends that don't
have low testosterone but they have
depression they have anxiety they have
low libido they have all very similar
symptoms so what I did before I stepped
into a doctor's office I remov those
variables you have that obligation you
should have that obligation for yourself
for your family for your own well-being
to come in to the as the best possible
man before you even decide to do
something to the best of your ability
because I understand when I had PFS it's
it was easier said than done I
understand that but it's very important
when when I say to the best of your uh
to the best of your ability so if you
can't run a marathon go outside for 10
minutes if you can't go out for 10
minutes do it for five minutes right if
you go to your pantry right now you can
do this while you have low testosterone
get rid of the trash that's in your in
your pantry you can do that before you
step foot in your doctor's office
because what that's going to do and as
Dr Keith nichel Nichols pointed out to
is if you get on if you get on hormone
replacement therapy and there's going to
be some time where you're going to
fluctuate and it's going to be some
crappy days some really good days and
it's going to be all over the place
right if you're on a boat and you're
going the wrong direction and now you're
adding hormone replacement you may be
going in the wrong direction a lot
faster because like I said you may start
seeing that it's not that easy of a
route right away it's going to take some
time and if you are if you have a
terrible provider it could be a very
long time right there's not not
everybody's Dr Keith Nichols right so
that's the thing so fix your variables I
can't stress this enough the calls I get
that say oh I uh yeah I think I have PFS
or I have low testosterone well what
what does your day look like I play I
play video games for five hours I'm
downstairs at my parents house in a
pitch black room just playing video
games do you go out with your friends no
I I I'm insecure and I left my friends
because you know my testosterone's low
do you do you do anything outside of
just being in your room no not I'm
waiting until my my hormones get
better men what the hell are you doing
stop that that nonsense get yourself to
the peak that you can and then work your
from there it just gets better it gets
better from when you're at your Optimum
place you can be without hormones to the
best of your
and then when you go to Dr Keith Nichols
and say Doc I'm fit to the best of my
ability my my my stress levels I've
learned to reduce that I'm spending more
time with my wife I've done you know if
you're spiritual if you're religious I'm
going to church now on Sundays I'm done
I've done everything I can doc here's
what I'm seeing in my blood work can you
work with me I promise you Dr Keith
Nichols will have a lot more success and
I'll let him speak to that than if you
come in
overweight sitting in your room all day
leaving your friends behind not talking
to your wife and being miserable and
then having Keith be your savior I just
don't think that's the Avenue we should
take yeah great great I think you agreed
Keith I will and I'll give you a couple
of other sides of the coin on that okay
so we can take the same 5 foot6 241
pound uh gentleman that Amir was talking
about and when we try to have that
conversation with them uh they'll be
sometimes they'll be the first to say
you know what no I eat good I exercise
regularly there's I you know I don't
have any
stress that's a problem that that's just
going to be a problem because we know
none of those can be true but yet their
perception is their reality and what I
found that you know if you you've got to
be an intelligent mature man that's
willing to step back and take a critical
analysis of his life and his habits and
those that are willing to do that
they'll succeed those that won't will
not you know there are there is not an
easy button you know when it when it
comes to doing what we do and when it
comes to changing those habits you
better get comfortable being
uncomfortable because those that can't
do that are not going to be successful
in what we do if you're not willing to
be hungry you're not going to lose
weight a lot of people to the to the age
I don't want to be hungry well then
you're not going to lose weight you have
to be in a choric deficit just as far as
weight loss goes so you got to be
comfortable being uncomfortable what
testosterone will do as we talked about
in one of our last podcasts is that look
it will reward effort but you got to put
in the effort that individual has to put
in The Sweat Equity and if they don't we
won't be successful so you know each
individual their perception is their
reality and I've learned that I cannot
change that I don't try to convince or
talk them into that anymore more I just
you know I'll do my best to optimize
their hormones and I will try to coach
them to some degree but if they're not
going to be reasonable about their own
input or lack thereof then they're not
going to have success and they'll be the
ones on forums and continue looking for
that easy button whether it be you know
the newest greatest peptide or this that
and the other instead of really getting
down to your foundation of Health which
is always nutrition exercise and hormone
optimization you have to do them all and
on the other side of a different coin
Amir is look there are some men out
there that are listening to that they're
going
look I want to get off the couch I want
to do something but I just can't I
literally have no energy my fatigue is
so great it feels like what a cancer
patient must be going through getting
radiation and chemotherapy I was that
guy as well I literally got to the point
where even though I didn't look the part
I was less than 10% body fat and you
know it was a mountain bike racer and
you know I just had a I just didn't fit
that bill but man I got to the point
where it was just a show I could get
through most of the day but around four
or five o'clock I hit that wall and I
was just exhausted and I was a miserable
human being and I couldn't do the things
that I always had done no matter how
much I wanted to and if I did I suffered
for days afterwards couldn't recover uh
and things just worse it were just worse
I just thought if I got enough sleep it
would all be better and then I almost
got addicted to ambian and Lunesta the
sleep a and so it was it was a it was a
nightmare for somebody that had always
been so active so here th those guys are
out there like that that want to so bad
so for you guys that really do have the
motivation and desire but you literally
can't not because you're too lazy
there's a difference the guys I've
talked about beforehand let's just I
hate to use that word but they're just
lazy they're gonna be absolutely and
then there's guys that don't want to be
lazy they literally have always lived an
active life the last thing they want to
be is lazy in fact they're ashamed that
they're being lazy they're you know
they're they're mad at themselves on a
constant basis that they can't do what
they've always done despite wanting to
every day and those guys yes
testosterone is a lifesaver it's a
lifesaver for me it's exactly why I do
what I do today I was that guy I went
through it I had a successful spot and
sports practice I was with all the pro
athletes UFC title fights with you know
the Nashville Predators of the hockey
league one of their Physicians for 10
years the the Tennessee Titans football
for two I mean I was dealing with pro
athletes and enjoyed every bit of it but
I was mismanaged misdiagnosed mistreated
by my own colleagues I had to figure
this out for myself and that's why I sit
here today talking to gentleman like you
is because of what I personally went
through so I see both sides of the coin
we got a side we got a side that that
knows there's something wrong and they
they don't know how to fix it and they
need someone to help them fix it and
then unfortunately some of those men
will find good providers and then some
will resort to forums and you know bad
providers and that's where you know the
Clash will occur with uh good advice
evidence-based advice versus non
evidence-based advice and so you T
touched on that on your PFS podcast
which is very great you've already
touched on a little bit here so I'd love
to hear more but yes I just was going to
give you the other side of the coin
because you know you you've been there
I've been there uh but but we weren't
that guy that that
just really never did learn to exercise
right eat correctly no what ever taught
him and you know and so we got a
different side and the hard part is
convincing those guys to get up and and
move to to improve the quality of their
life for not just them but for their
loved ones and everyone else as well I
absolutely agree with you and that's
that's a that's a good distinction
because I want to make it clear this is
not a blanket statement for everyone
however if you are somebody that's on
there and and and to attest to Dr what
Dr Keith Nichols said is I was that guy
too I could not keep my eyes open I have
a chain of restaurants here in San Diego
I would drive to my stores I'd have to
pull over and sleep it was mindboggling
for me and it was it was driving me
insane and and my wife would tell me you
know hey we're doing this with our
friends later on uh and we're going to
go to dinner with our best friends and I
say absolutely I would go uh to go get
dressed and I'd come back and say where
are we going and she' look at me like I
had Alzheimer's it was it was really
that bad so I get that so here's where
for those that are in that
situation okay I have the only advice I
would say is do the best you can and
don't beat yourself up okay don't beat
yourself up because guys like me I'm I'm
sure Dr Nichols like I'm I'm one of
those go go-getters as you can see I'm
very I I'm a go go go guy and the first
person I will beat up when I don't
succeed is myself and I've learned to
forgive myself for something that I had
no control over and it was very
difficult and that allowed me to open up
to myself and be more vulnerable to my
wife because what happened for me is I
would shut down I don't want other
people to know what's going on in my
world so a lot of guys that would in my
situation when they call me and say look
I'm not a weak man I used I I own a
business I'm a I'm a b i was a
bodybuilder I was this and that and then
I say well does your wife know or does
anyone know and they keep it to
themselves say no I'm I'm too I'm I'm a
man I don't talk and here's the thing
you
guys when we're when we're in this place
we can't do this alone find people that
you can discuss is this I trust me
here's what's crazy and when I to when I
had PFS okay when I finally opened up I
started to share with my other friends
you will not believe it I had three
close friends tell me that they they
took uh finast ride and they had similar
symptoms and I went why did you not tell
me and for the same reason as as we're
discussing they said well you know it's
embarrassing I'm a man and and I went
you know how you could have helped me
you could have helped 10 of you your
friends that are on finast R had you
shared that
so if you're there and you're listening
slow down for a minute take a breather
and know that you have people like Dr
Nichols there are good doctors out there
that can help you that want to be by
your side start creating the team to get
you closer to your health that's all I
will tell you and the team doesn't
necessarily have to be just a doctor a
team can be your your partner your your
your wife a close friend a therapist it
doesn't matter it could be whoever it is
but do not do this alone it's it's a
long process so yes in that respect uh
Dr Nichols I absolutely agree with
you awesome um Amir once uh as a man you
get in front of the doctor of the
provider for the first time what's the
mindset you need there um do you need to
be critical uh in well informed or do
you have to trust him and go with his
experience so you know for me it's an
interesting situation after a doctor
gave me a a drug that completely ruined
me I didn't trust any doctor I had I
mean the minute there they you know one
doctor tells me take this pill for hair
loss and he also told me um you're going
to have a lower chance of getting
prostate cancer with this pill so it's
twofer and then down the line I found
out I can't have sex with my wife for
five years um any doctor that said oh no
I can help you there's a big resistance
so there is a fine line between being
cynical and skeptical okay there's a
fine line between being cynical and
skeptical it was it and I will tell you
it was a hard process for me to find a
doctor because I went to a celebrity
hormone doctor that I thought was going
to give me the the the magic thing he
put me on a terrible protocol put me on
Arimidex which I didn't know what it was
at the time and that got me in a whole
host of other situations then I went to
another Doctor Who Amir not to interrupt
you but because that was in your first
video your PFS video and you're out in
California I can guess who you probably
saw based on the protoc protocol that
you outlined yeah okay probably starts
with an R I would guess yes and uh last
name with an m y the point is guys
that's correct don't get
misled by bright and shiny yeah don't
get just because they've got a big
YouTube following from bodybuilders or
this that and the
other packaging marketing don't get
sucked into that yeah not get sucked
into that because Amir thought he was
going the best of the best because we
get on and but yet you found out that
that's not really the case so you better
do a little more vetting uh not you but
you understand I mean now absolutely I I
I a different approach because you know
so much more now so I caught in I caught
that on your on your first podcast
that's exactly right it was excellent
and so you know uh please keep going but
the but the take-home message there is
guys you've got be careful in that the
ones that are getting the most hit out
there with the millions of followers or
however many they are hundreds of
thousands does not make them the best or
know exactly what they're doing or the
best for you that's just going to be the
truth we know them all we know them
inside and out and so let me that's just
Amir found out the hard way I found out
the hard way and I found I I I kept
finding out the hard way because after
that you know you get deflated you
thought you're going to the and and
these are not cheap doctors either these
are very expensive doctors I went to the
top of the top uh and I had to drive a
couple hours to see these you know
doctors I'm in San Diego so it wasn't
like I I I was willing to also fly to
Chicago I didn't care where I needed to
I I just wanted to get help so the
mindset I guess is do
and number two this is very important
okay and I'll I'll let Dr Nichols touch
on on how to find a proper provider
because that's not my that's not that's
above my pay grade but take your
time there is no rush I know I what I
mean by that
is when I go when I finally found a
proper doctor right who was Neil Dr Neil
rier trained they know what they're
doing I love I love my doctor now um he
actually mentioned for me to take my
time too which was really good right and
also the one thing that I realized
is if you have a good doctor if you have
a good doctor and that's where I'm going
to let him share how how to find one if
there is a way is listen to them don't
jump on on on social media and say my
doctor is making me do X Y and Z on all
this stuff should I change my prot call
tomorrow right in other words if you
have a proper provider the the the point
is he's monitoring he or she is
monitoring you trust the process and go
back to life I see so many people going
back to forums saying well I'm not going
to tell my doctor but I think I'm I'm
getting um a zit on my face so I'm going
to reduce my testosterone I'm increasing
my thyroid you're don't do that don't
listen to your provider slow down
and you know what'll be more more more
valuable go give your wife a kiss and a
hug go spend time with your kids
afterwards go go go go grab your wife
and and go get dinner go on a walk in
other words let your doctor do the
doctor thing and you go back and do life
again because I see do because I know
we've been burned so much we think it's
our job to ma now manage ourselves
manage our protocol and even manage our
doctors and I think it's a terrible idea
so set it and forget it and I'm going to
say this again because on the last video
I had all these people leave comments
and say um uh oh what do you mean said
it and forget it what if your doctor's
terrible I'm I'm gonna I'm gonna this
caveat is when you find a doctor like Dr
Nichols or the doctors that that have
been vetted set and forget it trust
their process and go back to life and Dr
Nichols I'll let you go from here well
know that's great advice there's nothing
more frustrating whenever you look on a
forum where you know it's inevitable you
go there right now on any of them hey
just sted me on all this what do you
think what should I do is this a good
there's nothing worse than that I mean
obviously they have no confidence in
their position whatsoever and then
they're willing to go on a forum where
you don't know anything about anybody
answering any of your questions when
else would you do that if you had cancer
any other major disorder would you just
go and take some advice from you know
Bill or Bob who's no telling where they
are they may not even be United States
but nonetheless you're getting advice
from someone that you know absolutely
nothing about if you probably met them
in person it would probably be the last
person got advice from and plus anybody
that's got try to be on forums giving
advice probably not going to be very
busy and doesn't have much of a life
otherwise because I've I'm always so
proud of my guys I don't really see any
of them on forums I used to scy them
just to see and I don't have the time
anymore but I'm so proud because my job
is to get them optimal where they don't
have to worry about exactly what air is
trying to say is that you get your you
know you got to get with the tradition
that get your hormones optimal where you
realize just check that box and go on
and spend time with your wife your kids
your you know your friends your hobby
you know your work your career that's
the real that's that's the goal that
that is the whole goal you're not
thinking about it all the time and
that's really what optimization is when
you wake up it becomes just like putting
on your deodorant or putting in your
hair gel or whatever you may do in the
morning uh the same thing you just don't
even think about it anymore we have good
days bad days good weeks bad weeks good
libido days weeks bad just part of part
of being human part of life but to touch
on what Amir did say is that
look there's so many t- mills put up on
every corner now you can't get on social
media at all without some you know
online testosterone Clinic I'd be
careful about any of those yes for the
most of the guys that just want to get
on for performance enhancement oh it's
great for them but we're talking about
people that truly want to do it for
health and prevention and for a longterm
with their provider they want a
long-term relationship with them if if
you go to a website and there's no
physician listed that's a big red flag
right away who's treating you who's
dictating care you know yeah I got it
it's your you know celebrity on YouTube
or whoever and they've hired some you
know wounded physician that you know
they won't even name on their website to
do your treatment that that's that's
kind of a red flag there but first and
foremost if you're having to go to a
form to ask questions that probably
means that if you don't trust your
physician or you don't have access to
them now that that that's a problem in
of itself now like it or or hate it all
my guys females they have complete
access to me seven days a week I mean I
answer my messages every day all day
long long and even on weekends so
there's never a time and when it comes
to you know when it comes to treating
patients look it's an informed patient
is a is is a really good patient so if
someone comes in and asks for instance
what AM Mir went through hey Doc I'm
losing my hair I want to start
finasteride well okay Bill but I'm going
to send you some literature and these
are the risks that you're willing to
accept if you start
finasteride so the point is is that they
should be willing to provide you with
medical literature on about any topic
that you may want concerning hormones or
medications associated with hormone use
like for hair loss so access is I think
is
critical I don't use any intermediaries
I don't have a nurse practitioner or PA
I mean I you know it's always been this
way it's the way I wanted it set up I
didn't want to be the 800 pound gorilla
and you know like some of these multip
specialy clinics are I deal with every
man on an individual basis like it or
hate it but that that's the that's the
way that is so I do agree on you there
Amir but if you don't if you don't if
you have to resort to a
forum then we have a problem one place
or the other whether it be with the
provider that you've got or you yourself
don't trust him for whatever reason you
you need to find that provider that's
willing to provide you with the
information and answer your questions
and look we as providers the ones that
are Neil rier trained that are you know
he's my good friend and colleague I
always have to make a shout out to him I
talk to him on a weekly basis he's just
just a a great friend and and a mentor
but look we're not here to always tell
you what you want to hear we're here to
improve the quality of your life and
just like when I was dealing with the
pro athletes and watching the coach deal
with those professionals we'll treat you
like sometimes we have to tell you
things you don't want to hear you know
so so that that's the problem and you
know take a testost let me excuse my
language here I used to say it all the
time but I'll say but look it doesn't
lie a fire into your ass you have do
that yourself you you've got to once you
get it you've got to do that yourself
and you know lying to your provider yeah
doc I'm eating right I'm exercising
right but I'm still having all these
other issues be be upfront and honest
and that's what I'm so proud about my
population men is my proudest days are
whenever I'll see a follow-up form the
yearly followup whatever doc man I'm
having these issues I'm doing great
otherwise but look I'm only having those
issues because this is what I'm going
through I'm having related to this it's
not has nothing to do with hormones my
hormones are awesome man thank you so
much those guys got it they understand
and they'll say that I'm just you know
not sleeping well and you know I'm just
I'm little beos down a little because
I'm working 14 hours days and really
stressed about projects got going on
those are the great guys to treat
because they're they're just realists
they understand that we're all human and
hormones don't make us superhuman these
guys on forums think that you can tweak
these hormones during periods of stress
and always have this
sustained period of Nirvana that that's
never going to occur guys life is not
fun life is not easy life is hard and uh
you just got to roll with the punches
and testosterone doesn't necessarily
make that any easier it just makes you a
a person that can address those things
without having symptoms of a deficiency
that's a and and also we got to touch on
this fact that you see it all the time I
feel great I feel awesome that misleads
so many people out there Stephen Amir
and myself we don't feel awesome all the
time we don't feel great all the time we
do
not look when we talk about how great we
feel Amir especially myself especially I
don't know Stephen went through the
severe symptoms of deficiency he
probably smart enough to catch it
earlier than I was but nonetheless look
we're it's a relative term relative I
feel great compared to how I felt before
that doesn't mean I feel great every day
so those guys out there they mishar that
and they think they're going to feel
great all the time and when they don't
when they have these down week or two
then something must be wrong no that's
just not true and and we'll get messages
where look let's all be up front an
audit we'll get me Doc I've I've had
fatigue for the last you know for 10
days and I've you know my lito hadn't
been where it should be okay well join
the crowd that happens to all of us okay
thanks for letting me know but look we
don't those those kind of guys we can't
just tweak something real quick and make
that go away because if you if you just
say look all right give it another 10
days inevitably you don't give a phone
call back in the 99.99% of the time
because it just comes full circle back
around that's just part of life and we
we don't need to you know make it out to
be something that it's not we're
improving symptoms of an efficiency
that's what we're doing we're trying to
take a person and make them a normal
human being that was having symptoms
related to low testosterone that's all
that it is we make them a normal man
not a deficient man that that's all it
is I love that that's very well
said yeah that's a great Point Keith you
don't need to change of protocol because
uh you have a few days that you aren't
feeling that great that's an excellent
point anything you want to add there
Amir no the only thing that I would say
is like there's something that I in my
coaching I talk about something called
Roi which many of you guys know which is
return on investment versus
rol right which is return on life right
when we do a return on investment versus
return on life return on investment
right which is you know what uh what can
I get from this doctor what's going to
happen and then it's constantly worrying
about fixing your numbers fixing like
fixing all the medical stuff meanwhile
forgetting to return back to life I will
stress this out over and over again
right when I when with being on
testosterone and Dr Nichols pointed out
I had PFS I went from where I was
absolutely miserable to quote unquote
feeling great but you're absolutely
right you speak to my wife and she says
you don't want to you're not having sex
with me all the time you're not we're
not going at it twice a day or all that
nothing we're I have work I have we have
a daughter I'm exhausted we we'd rather
watch sometimes a movie then get down
and that's just what happens right I'm
45 years old but with that being said
the most important factor on this
investment is I got to go back to life
so when I when I'm tired welcome to the
human race I'm tired until the next day
when I'm not I'll take advantage of the
there's days where I bad mood right so I
am in a bad mood until I'm not and when
I'm in a good mood I take advantage of
it why do I take advantage of it because
I knew how it felt before I was on
testosterone replacement and incredibly
grateful for being where I'm at today so
I'll take the bad days I'll take the
days where I'm tired I'll take the days
where I'm I'm uh bitter or angry or
depressed for a day I'll take that any
day from where I was before I'm so even
though it's relative I'm extremely
grateful for where I'm at today but I
still have human days that's the whole
point we're going back to being human
right I was subhuman before where I just
felt like crap a lot more days than I
did that I do now but I'm now grateful
for the highs and I'm graceful with my
lows okay I'm very grateful that I feel
good and I try to be graceful to the
best that I can when I'm not feeling
good and that's okay now now for those
that are like man I can't wait to get on
testosterone you can practice that as
you are on your journey going on trt you
can practice being grateful when you're
feeling good you may not be as good as I
feel right now you might your your Peaks
and lows might be like just like that
but G be be grateful when you have a
moment of
clarity and don't beat yourself up when
you're down and then when you work with
Dr Nichols you're G to be more grateful
when you have more High highs and still
be graceful when you're on your lows in
other words this the framework still
doesn't change you just hopefully feel a
little better but don't forget you can't
out Human Being Human there's no drug
that you will take that will out human
you being a human what does that mean
you're going to have great days bad days
you're GNA have good moods you're gonna
have bad moods you're goingon to feel
insecure about your money today and you
feel secure about your money tomorrow
you're gonna have every single thing
that when you go to the bookstore and
you go to self-help section that's
there's a reason the the self-help
section is bigger than the hormone
section it should be the hormones and
stuff that should be bigger because most
of us should should learn on how our
body works but it's the self-help
section because why why because no
matter what you who you are and what you
are it's The Human Condition to feel our
ups and
downs everything Amir just said uh
should be packaged and sold it was just
pure pure gold it was worth the price of
admission everything he just said we can
actually just cut everything else out
and just put that right in there and uh
and and package it as is Stephen it
couldn't could have been said any better
I really appreciate it Amir and I'm just
going to make sure everybody understands
we've all been on hormones been on it
for years Steven's in excellent shape
amir's excellent shape blah blah blah
look Amir Stephen do we have erections
every morning any of us yeah yeah do we
do we have a rage in libido all the
time do we feel like Steph is even you
do you feel like working out every day
and do you get a big good workout every
day not every day no of course you don't
do you have to force yourself sometimes
to go when you don't want to Sure Amir
you the same 100% 100% up there thinking
that and they do they do think this way
because they see it on
forums look it that is not what
testosterone does and that's what I
always try to just to be so honest with
our patients and everyone and you guys
are so good at it to let's tell you the
truth about what it does and doesn't do
and so you know the problem is you got
all these younger guys and their teens
and early 20s well hell I probably had
an Direction every day by then probably
y did too I don't know but can't
remember that that far but nonetheless a
lot different when you start getting
into your late 30s and 40s and 50s is a
there's a big difference okay it's a big
difference we need to cherish all the
wonderful days that we have on it and
understand we're still going to have bad
ones and like I said before on a
previous podcast with Stephen it's like
the guys that are in their late 20s
really starting their early 30s where
life really becomes real and uh I use
the word stress and they they kind of
misinterpret that because everybody
thinks that stress has to be bad stress
no stress does not weddings are
stressful or you know getting ready for
a podcast be stressful even though it's
not bad stress it's just it's stress but
I'll make a different word when you
start getting your you know late 20s
early 30s you're usually married by then
you probably have young children you're
working on your career you know You' got
a house payment a car payment you got a
you know got to got to take care of the
house got to take care of the yard look
those are responsibilities so when
increased responsibilities yeah if you I
I'll use that word that's stressful but
increased responsibilities you don't
have time to think about your libido
every day or whether you got an erection
or not or you know and sometimes you're
just too damn tired to come home and
work out because you've been doing all
those things so uh that's testosterone
doesn't make us impervious to life as
Amir so eloquently you know stated so I
just want to make sure we're all real
clear on that is that getting on
testosterone is not going to make you
have a raging libido and and air the
problem with guys is that the ones that
do really bad or have a really hard time
are those with very specific
expectations because what they've read
and heard from other men online or on
forums mainly if you have a very
specific expectation about what it's
going to do for you like I'm gonna have
this libido I'm gonna have you know
erection every morning I'm gonna just
jump out of bed and want to go work out
and it's just going to be great you're
going to be disappointed because it's
not going to do that for you it's just
not going to do that for you and I don't
want you to be disappointed I want you
to have at least some people out there
that say he told me the truth he he told
me he he he kind of told me what it was
really going to be like not this you
know magical Paradise where as you
talked about in the beginning of the
podcast where the sky is blue the grass
is green every day birds are singing and
you just it's not that way guys it's not
going to be that way all right so so
don't don't look for it to be and you'll
be much happier it works in everybody
young and old male and female it works
the same way it provides you with the
same benefits and if you don't get
better in certain areas with optimal
testosterone levels it's not
testosterone and that's where you have
to be mature enough smart enough to
address the other issues that may be at
cause okay that that's all I that's my
you know two cents worth in addition to
what you had to say Amir you know Keith
I I want to point out to what you said
that's actually good news I want you
guys to hear what he just said you know
why it's good news that means it's your
choice then because if you're waiting
for a drug to make you happy or to make
your life different you're going to be
in trouble what what Dr Keith just
pointed out to is that it's it's UN in
our we want it to be in our control that
responsibility of being able to get
better being able to be in in a
different situation if we are strictly
relying on a medical doctor to give our
life back you're going to be in in
you're not going to be in for a treat
now the doctor will facilitate and make
your life better yes if your hormones
are bad but do not
wait men for somebody else to fix your
eating habits your workout habits your
relationship with your wife your time
with yourself getting off the forums
your doctor cannot be there for all that
stuff that's in your control and you
have no idea how impactful that that
stuff alone is right so here's something
that I'm going to leave off with is we
cannot F we cannot I I wrote this down
this is so important no one chooses the
disease but we choose our Focus okay
this is something I'm going to say it
again we do not choose our sickness or
disease but right this minute man we can
choose what we focus on so are you going
to spend after this after this podcast
going oh yeah you know what that was
great but but this guy on this forum
says I need to put a coffee enema in my
butt and like and I'm and that joking
aside I had someone email me and say Hey
you know I have low testosterone someone
said to put a coffee Ana it'll clean
your liver and I'm going that's where
you're at right now like like you could
have spent that 10 minutes building a
better future building a better present
and instead you're sitting there
ruminating and here's the here's the
other
situation if you don't fix the
rumination now I promise you you're GNA
have a lot more to ruminate once you get
on hormones I promise you because you're
gonna have we I went through all these
fluctuations and changes and so
fix slowing down you can't can't choose
you can't you can't you didn't choose
the disease but you can choose the focus
if you notice yourself ruminating settle
yourself
relax okay and then when you get on
testosterone settle yourself and
relax before you get on hormones go out
of Nature and have fun but when you get
on testosterone this is really important
go out in nature and have fun do you see
what's happening what Dr Nichols has
been pointing to is go be human now and
just be a better human once you're on
testosterone if it helps you but you
have to do human things in the process
you cannot stop living you cannot just
do nothing you got to go back to rool go
to a return on your life it will make a
difference right and so if if if and and
I I have a feeling when Dr Nicholls is
honest with some people they probably
don't want to hear it and so he might be
the guy that's the bad guy in this oh
well my doctor said I need to change my
sleep habits diet and all this I'll go
to the Magic Bullet I'm going to
disappoint you and I'm I'm Dr Nichol
will say the
same this hour was the Magic Bullet we
just gave you the Magic Bullet there is
no magic bullet that's it and if you're
waiting for one you're going to go and
disappoint yourself with the with the
doctors that are on YouTube and these
magical doctors that that are giving
going to give you the magic bullet for
you know thousands of dollars and then
you're going to go back to probably Dr
Nichols after you spent a lot of money
and he's going to say go back to the
basics folks this is this is the magic
this is the the behind the curtains The
Wizard of Oz there is no magic bullet
there is no magic it's
patience having the right protocol and
taking your time and having fun in the
process and loving your life loving your
family loving your job to to the best of
your ability until we die
and that's it and then we go on with our
life and so like that's that's all I
have to say for the day and and I I
don't think that I don't know if there's
much to to talk about after this well
not really I I will say that you know if
you're going to a doctor that tells you
what you want to hear just to keep you
happy that's probably not the one I
would want to go to I want to go to an
honest one I want one to tell me manto
man the truth whether I like it or not
and I like that in all aspects of my
life uh my friends a true friend's going
to tell me when I ask them a question I
really want the truthful answer and that
that is the the the true definition of a
friend those that will and so I I do try
to do that and that you know some people
may not be as responsive as others
because we're not used to that in life
anymore everything's got to be
sugarcoated but you know I'm there to
get them results and sometimes they you
have to kind of give them the the
coaches talk if you if you will I use it
that and when I tell me in that first
start getting back to your 56 241 is
that look what I try to say is look
let's let's start a new you uh when you
get testosterone this needs to be the
first day of your new life what you need
to do before that is you need to clean
all your house out of all that bad food
that you've been eating clean it all out
because if it's not there you can't eat
it and don't go by but start and just
fill it with nutritious food and then
you've got to start with baby steps we
don't expect you to go right into the
gym the first day but look anything you
do today whether it be a few push-ups or
walking to the mailbox back it's more
than you did yesterday and take that
approach every day anything I do today
is more than I did the day before and
then just keep let that build on itself
and you'll ultimately get where you want
to be it's a marathon not a Sprint we
all know that you got to be patient with
testosterone I I I see the really the
the physical the sexual the the mental
aspects all coming together really most
nicely between months six through 12 and
they improve yearly but that is with
them putting in The Sweat Equity you got
to put in The Sweat Equity with that
you'll see results once again a real
reward effort but that effort is hard to
start with for all of us it's hard for
all of us when you haven't been doing it
it's it's hard you got to be disciplined
like Amir was not everyone's as is as
disciplined as he was and had that
strength and you know determination but
take it from him and what he said as you
guys wake up say I want amir's strength
determination I want his Dom discipline
his commitment I'm willing to sacrifice
like he was in order to get where I want
to be when you wake up and you do that
you'll be successful and until you do
you will not it here I go again I'm
going to say a bad
word half ass in half ass results out
you can't half ass it as our coaches
would always say you got to be Allin
guys yeah all aspects oh there's my
daughter okay uh oh soap in my
mouth that's my little girl and you know
what here's the thing I will end it with
if you have a family right get off this
podcast look at your wife straight in
the eye look at your daughter in the eye
she'll Arya come here hurry hurry
hurry come here come here I want I want
you guys to hear this out why does daddy
work
out to get strong for who me for you
right whenever I'm in the gym and she'll
she's in the gym with me I do every set
that I do I think about every single rep
that I do this one's for my wife this is
for my daughter this one's for my health
make commitments right now uh uh
gentlemen like when you're waiting for
testosterone to make you masculine you
can have a masculine mindset right now
don't wait for the testosterone you're
just going to be a a better man if your
hormones get uh situated but practice
being a better man now like you know
what I mean like the way like I'm I I
have a successful business but I had a
successful mindset before I got my
business you guys know story you give
someone that has a bad mindset a million
dollar lottery ticket in a year it goes
away you give a successful guy a
business owner a 100,000 he'll make it
to two million by the end of the year
it's the same thing put in The Sweat
Equity now right so when you're on
hormone replacement therapy you will be
unstoppable yes you're going to have
those bad days but practice that now go
do like Dr Nicholls said if you can't do
10 push-ups do one I don't care do one
because then you're saying I made a
commitment to myself right by the end of
two weeks you'll be at three you'll
you'll tripled it right and that makes
that becomes an exponential process and
you start seeing it in all other areas
of your life here's another thing you
can do you can get off this podcast once
you hear it and say uh to your wife I
have not been transparent to myself and
to you I'm G to be a better man today
you don't even have to you don't even
have to do a push-up you can be the
person that you want to be a year from
now right this minute there's nothing
stopping us from doing that I'm not I
don't have any special skills that Dr
Nichols or Dr DeVos has I don't have it
I just made a
decision because right now folks that
are on here that are that are not where
you want to be you're making a DEC
decision too you made a decision not to
be the person you want also a decision
all right so make the decision to be the
person you want to be so if you need to
get a pen and paper and say who who do I
need to be in order to it's very simple
write it down make a list and put it on
your wall I did that and here I am today
people say oh it's easy for you to say
because you have muscles it's because
you have a business it's it's easy for
me to say because I had some point I had
to make hard decisions in the past so
the hard decisions in the past allowed
me to have the easy decisions you think
I'm making today you have that
opportunity use it you can be a victim
or you can persevere like air did he
persevered he
persevered yeah this was golden guys
thank you so much I think it will be a
lot appreciated by a lot of men
considering uh getting on
trt thank you so much both you guys for
having me honestly it it I feel like I'm
I'm I'm talking to one of my favorite
people I have never met you and I'm so
glad that we got to do this together
it's exactly what I imagine Dr DeVos
thank you for entrusting me with your
group and uh gentlemen it was pleasure
Amir you're welcome wonderful wonderful
podcast there you did a wonderful job my
friend I hope you're I know you're
already extremely successful but uh
hopefully more of the health coaching
will be in in store for everyone as well
I appreciate that you guys thank you
yeah you did very well thank you so much
both of you and enjoy the rest of your
weekend you too
pleasure